All right, folks, we are now ready to start working with Java,
creating some really nice programs and see how it is
like to to program in Java to develop applications in Java.
And the first thing that you require on your systems is the JDK.
That is the Java development kit,
which is you can think about it as being the toolbox that you require to run
everything Java that is right Java,
compile, run, and execute, execute applications which are created in Java as well.
And for doing that, but first the JDK, it also includes the JRE and the JVM.
The JRE is the environment, the Java runtime environment,
which is used to run Java programs.
The Java virtual machines, the JVM is the one that you give the bytecode to,
and which understands the bytecode for your machine.
And that is the one player that is responsible for the Java tagline right once,
run anywhere.
So all of those are part of the JDK,
so you don't need to worry about to download them separately.
You just need the JDK and everything comes bundled.
And for doing that, as you see on my browser,
I've just gone on into my search engine and and I've searched for JDK.
You go to the Oracle official website, they say at the time,
I'm recording this video, Java 25 has been released.
It's the latest stable version and because of the aggressive model of Java
development, which I was mentioning earlier,
there release a new major version every six months.
But currently at the time, I'm recording this video, JDK 25 is the latest one.
But Java 21 is there, earlier versions are already there also there.
And it takes a lot of time for project teams to upgrade to newer versions.
Why is that? Because a lot of code is already written.
It's in production, life running in customer environments.
And just because a new major version is released,
they don't want to spoil the party, right?
And that's why companies don't take the risk.
So they take a lot of time, have patience and then switch to a newer version.
And that's why at the time, I'm recording this video again,
chances are teams are still working on Java 8, JDK 11 or at max Java 17
as there as the latest Java version, right?
But for now, you can just go on and install JDK 25 or JDK 21 on your systems.
And based on the operating system that you're using with the Linux macOS Windows,
it has the appropriate links to download.
For me, it is Mac OS. So I have downloaded and installed Java for Mac OS on my system.
But you can just go on and download Linux or Windows as well.
And once you do that, how do you know if Java was installed successfully?
And which version is the is the one that you have on your system on Windows?
You can just go on to command prompt terminal.
But on Mac, we appropriately call it the terminal,
even on Linux environments.
So I'll just open my terminal window for you.
And I'll just say Java hyphen hyphen version.
And there you are, it says that Java 25.0.1 is installed on my system.
And I said, JRE is a part of that already JVM is also included.
But this is the one proof that you require that Java is already installed.
The next step is we need an IDE that is an integrated development environment.
There are choices like Eclipse, there is a visual studio code.
But there is an intelligent and for the school sphere,
prefering using IntelliJ because it's been the number one Java IDE for many years now.
And based on its simplicity, its minimalist behavior and its modern as well.
And it's lightweight on your systems as well.
So and we can just go on, open up a new tab and I can search for IntelliJ.
So you go to the IntelliJ ID official website.
And it says the leading ID for professional development in Java and Kotlin.
Obviously, any company can claim that, but but here JetBrains is quite right and saying that
because as I said, it's been the leading ID for Java developers for quite some while now.
Just click on download and just install it again for your system.
And it says it has the free one with a 30 day ultimate subscription trial included.
For this course, I've just, I'm just using the free one because as I said,
I just want to start it from absolute scratch, cater to everyone, whether they have the free
or the paid one, but even if you have the paid one, that's perfectly fine.
So once you download it, we'll just go on and open up IntelliJ.
And you just click a new project quickly and it automatically selects Maywin archetype.
Now, what is Maywin?
It is the number one build tool for Java applications.
I'll just leave a link to my YouTube mini course on Maywin.
What is it and how do we use it?
Why do we use it?
And also put in one video in the middle or the end of the scores for you to understand what
Maywin is, but for now, just understand that it is used for interoperability between different
IDEs and it's a Java build tool, right?
And all you have to do is for now, you just name that Maywin project.
I'll just scroll it, for example, start Java. And the location is downloads,
but you can just go on and change that as per your preference.
And then JDK automatically selects the JDK 25.0.1, which we just installed by the way,
but you can just go on and choose a JDK, which is not recent, but you might prefer that.
But for now, I'll just prefer the latest one.
Keep the catalog as internal archetype as search for Maywin archetype quickstart,
which just gives you a Maywin barebones project which you can just run, right?
No settings, no configurations need to be done, you get a project that just runs.
Keep the version two, let's say 1.0 and click on advanced settings group IDE,
which in Maywin is, again, in that Maywin video, you'll find in detail what a group ID is,
but for now, just what your group, what group you follow, what group you work in, or your organization,
or your company, for now, I'll just skip it to org.waq.
And then I'll just keep the version in that, if I read the same hitcreate.
Goes on, and it just opens up that window for you, as you can see.
Let me just maximize that, close this promise symbol for now, and I'll not do any settings,
I'll not do any configurations, because as I said, we're choosing a Maywin archetype quickstart,
we get a Maywin project, we get a Java project that we can just run.
Let's go on to source, where SRC short for source, where Java files live in,
main and Java, and then an org.waq, which is my package name, just open the app file,
and let me just make it a bit larger for you, and maximize this, and see.
So we've got some code, and as promised, we can just run. So the explanation, I do in a bit,
but for now, I'll just go on and click this green arrow, run after Java, and in a short while,
at the bottom, you'll see the hello world, right, which obviously was printed, thanks to the line,
but 11, right. So that is, you got your JDK installed it, you have your ID, it's running, right,
that's the great part. So we are all set to understand how Java works, how to create
your Java programs, and how to actually write your first Java program, and I'm going to make
you understand what this jargon is all about in the next video. I'll see you then.